Hello everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we're talking all
about cars in this
intermediate level lesson.
That's right. We have a little bit
of problems with our car and we're
going to talk about some possible
solutions to these car problems we have.
So why don't we just listen to the dialogue
today. We have no words on vocabulary
previous so let's jump right into the
dialogue and listen for the first time.
My car won't start.
Stupid old car. Hold on.
Before you kick your car let's go
through some possible problems.
Fine. Ok first of all can you turn
the key in the ignition? Yeah I'm here
with my friend and he thinks it may
be the spark plug or the starter motor.
Those are possible problems but tell me when you turn
the key do you hear the starter motor crank? Yeah
it sounds like it usually does when I start the car
but nothing else happens. The engine won't start.
Should I maybe press the accelerator?
No if you step on the accelerator
pedal you can flood the carburetor
and your car will never start.
So what do you think it is? I know this
may seem like a silly question but does
your car have gasoline? Yeah right I
got the car started. Thanks for your help.
I told you to fill the tank.
Ok so this dialogue reminds me
a lot of a radio show in America
called Car Talk and the hosts of
the show like Marco and I today.
They talk about how to
solve problems and they
ask you questions to find
out what the problem is.
So it's a really helpful show but
let's take a look at some of the phrases
and words that you heard so we can
understand what exactly is going on here.
Language takeaway. All right so today on language
takeaway we have five words and there are very specific
to the car so why don't we start with the first word
it's a noun and we are talking about the ignition.
Ignition. The ignition is the first step to the ignition
is a part of the first step to starting a car. Basically
under the wheel of the car the steering wheel there
is usually a silver hole where you can put the key in.
This is the ignition it starts the car.
Exactly so you put the key in the ignition
and you can start the car and to start the
car means to turn it on to get it going.
That's right and so ignition is the first step
starting the ignition. Ok so moving on to our
next word we have a word that's formed by two
different parts a spark plug, a spark plug.
So a spark plug is an electrical
object basically this has
to do with electricity and the
way that the car gets energy.
So it's called a spark
plug because it creates
a spark which is a
brief burst of current.
So this basically creates a
small spark of electricity and
this makes the gasoline ignite
so that's what makes the car go.
So energy is taken from
the battery to start a small
fire basically so which
then starts the engine.
Spark plug it's a very small
but very important part of a car.
Very good and moving on we have
the starter motor. Ok to be very honest
with you I'm not a car person so
I'm not sure what the starter motor is.
Maybe you can explain this to us Marco.
Ok so basically your car runs on gasoline.
So you put your key into the
ignition and you turn it right.
This in turn sends energy to this little motor
called a starter motor and that basically
gets the car going by means of an electrical
current before the gasoline ignites.
So it's like a little electrical motor that
makes the spark plug ignite and causes
some of the mechanical parts like the pistons
move within the car and then it turns on.
Ok so again this is all
about the beginning when
we turn the key in the
ignition what happens.
This is a starter motor.
So once we've turned the car on
we've turned the key in ignition.
We have to worry about
giving the car gas so
we can control gas with
the accelerator pedal.
So by saying you want to
give the car gas as you want
to give it more energy, more
power or less energy right.
Right so if I want to go very
fast I push my foot down on the
accelerator and the further
down it goes the faster I move.
Exactly so that's the accelerator.
Now the opposite of
making the car go would
make the car stop and
those are called brakes.
So on the left we have a brake pedal and
on the right we have an accelerator pedal.
Very good.
Ok and talking about
acceleration and gas we have a very
specific mechanical object
and that's called a carburetor.
Ok again carburetor I
know that this is under
the hood of my car but
I'm not sure what it does.
Let's talk about this.
Alright so it's not very common to have a
carburetor anymore in new cars but basically
it's a small device that controls the flow
of gasoline from the gas tank to the engine.
Basically what it does it creates it makes
the gasoline into a type of a very thin
mist and that's what caught in that way and
that way the gasoline can ignite easier.
So the further down you push your foot
on the accelerator the wider the little
gap or the hole will open on the carburetor
and that way your car will go faster.
Alright very good.
So that's all we've got for
language take away today but don't
go anywhere we'll be back in
a second with fluency builder.
My car won't start.
Stupid old car.
Hold on before you kick your car let's
go through some possible problems.
Fine.
Ok first of all can you
turn the key in the ignition?
Yeah I'm here with my
friend and he thinks it
may be the spark plug
or the starter motor.
Those are possible problems
but tell me when you
turn the key do you hear
the starter motor crank?
Yeah it sounds like it
usually does when I start the
car but nothing else
happens the engine won't start.
Should I maybe press the accelerator?
No if you step on the
accelerator pedal you can
flood the carburetor and
your car will never start.
So what do you think it is?
I know this may seem like a silly
question but does your car have gasoline?
Yeah right I got the car
started thanks for your help.
I told you to fill the tank.
Alright we're back so now
what do we take a look at four
key phrases that we have
for you on fluency builder?
Fluency builder.
Ok this first phrase.
So you heard the phrase at the beginning
car trouble center but car trouble center.
That's maybe the name
of a fake company that we
use but the phrase car
trouble is very very common.
So if you say I'm having car trouble or I
had some car trouble what does that mean?
That means my car broke.
Ok but you don't say my car broke.
This is one thing that can't break
because normally you say I'm having
trouble or I'm having car trouble
because a part of my car is not working.
Ok so instead of saying I'm having
problems with my car or my car
broke you just say I had car
trouble or I'm having car trouble.
That's right so this is a really
good excuse for coming to work late.
You can say I'm so sorry I was
having car trouble this morning.
Right so any type of
problems with your car can be
considered car trouble
flat tire no battery etc.
Okay now moving on we have
a very interesting verb here.
We heard when the guy
was talking about the starter
motor he said do you hear
the starter motor crank?
Ok to crank so this is a very
interesting verb it can also be a noun.
It's a sound.
Ok but it's also a movement.
So when something turns
around in a circle don't think
maybe you think of a metal
wheel don't think that's a crank.
So sometimes we talk about
those old cars you know in 1910s
1920s the first Ford cars you
had to crank them in the front.
You had to actually turn with your
hand a wheel to make the car start.
So this is a crank.
Exactly you can hear this in
your car maybe if your car doesn't
have gasoline you hear that
that's the starter motor cranking.
So it's going around in circles
trying trying to create energy.
Exactly and now when the guy was talking
about the accelerator and he was talking about
the carburetor he said no don't step on that
pedal because you can flood the carburetor.
So to flood.
Ok to flood this is a verb maybe you've
heard the word flood before us a noun
but this means to fill something with
liquid with gasoline with water with milk.
So to flood something is
to fill it up with the liquid.
Ok very good so you can
flood a dam for example right.
That's right or in this case
you can flood a carburetor
which means it won't
work because it's all wet.
Ok very good and the last
phrase that we have very handy
when you're talking
about cars is to fill the tank.
Ok this is always a problem at my house
because I hate to fill the tank really.
Yeah whenever my car is in the driveway and
someone in my family asks if they can borrow it so
yeah sure and then obviously an hour later they
come back and say why don't you ever fill the tank.
It's empty you have no gas.
I say well I hate to fill
the car with gas and so I
always have an empty
tank so I never fill the tank.
Ok so that's what it means
to fill the tank is to have it full
of gasoline right to put
gasoline into your gasoline tank.
Very good why don't we go
back and listen to the dialogue for
the last time and we'll be
back to talk a little bit more.
(music)
Car-Trowel Center, how may I help you?
My car won't start. Stupid old car.
Hold on before you kick your car
let's go do some possible problems.
Fine.
Ok first of all can you
turn the key in the ignition?
Yeah I'm here with my
friend and he thinks it
may be the spark plug
or the starter motor.
Those are possible problems
but tell me when you
turn the key do you hear
the starter motor crank?
Yeah it sounds like it
usually does when I start the
car but nothing else
happens the engine won't start.
Should I maybe press the accelerator?
No if you step on the
accelerator pedal you can
flood the carburetor and
your car will never start.
So what do you think it is?
I know this may seem like it's silly
question but does your car have gasoline.
Um yeah right I got the car
started thanks for your help.
I told you to fill the tank.
(music)
Alright we're back so
talking about cars and car
trouble I understand for
example in some countries
when you're getting a
driver's license you're forced
or obliged to learn a
little bit of car mechanics.
You have to learn about
the engine or how to
change your tire and
basic things like this.
That's a brilliant idea.
In America you don't have
to know how to fix your car.
Uh you have to know how
to pay someone to fix your
car but basically we only
learn the rules of the road.
So the signs and the basic rules.
Really?
Yeah but I think it will be
very helpful to know how
to fix a tire or how to
change the oil in your car.
I mean is this a requirement in Ecuador?
Yeah yeah when you're getting your
driver's permit your driver's license
you have to take a course which
shows you the mechanics of the car.
First aid course and also
basic road rules and all that
stuff but basically because it
can be something very simple.
Like for example they show
you where the battery is,
where you can check the
oil and basic things like this.
So maybe the little
cable from the battery just
came loose and that's
why your car won't start.
So instead of you waiting for two hours until
somebody comes and picks you up or a tow truck you can
just check very briefly basic things that can maybe
go wrong in your car and you can just go in your way.
That's awesome.
I had my dad for that.
My dad said I'm not going to
have a little girl who doesn't know
how to change a tire or who doesn't
know how to check the oil level.
Yeah but not everybody has
a parent who will teach them.
Right knowing it's very handy
because for example you get a flat tire.
And sometimes you know
cars can be a little bit tricky.
The wheel nuts are
sometimes covered by a plastic
cover so you don't
know how to take it off.
There's a special tool for that.
Or the jack sometimes
the jack is not the normal
one that you have to
like pump up and down.
It's a little one that you have to
turn a lever and you have to do this.
So it's very very useful
to know these things.
Absolutely. I'm curious
to know if our listeners out
there have experience
with cars and car mechanics.
And if you have this rule like Marco
says they have an Ecuador about
learning about cars before you
actually get your driver's license.
Let us know on our website EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you there.
All right guys. Bye.